Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Sidney Ralph Bernstein Company History Files, 1873-1964 RL.00667
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Sidney Ralph Bernstein Company History Files
1873-1964
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.00667
4 Linear Feet
3000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Sidney Ralph Bernstein Company History Files were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by the J. Walter Thompson Company in 1987.
Historical Note
Chronology
1962, Feb.-1964, July Executives in the J. Walter Thompson Company begin to discuss the preparation of a publication for the company's centennial year; potential authors are reviewed
1963, July Sidney Ralph Bernstein agrees to write the history; granted leave from Advertising Age where he was Editorial Director
1963, Aug. Marianne Keating, a J. Walter Thompson Company staff member, assigned as Bernstein's research assistant
1963-1964 Research materials collected, interviews conducted
1964, Sept. Manuscript reviewed by Norman H. Strouse
Collection Overview
The Sidney Ralph Bernstein Company History Files span the years 1873 to 1964, but the bulk of the material dates from 1963 to 1964. The collection consists primarily of research files containing transcripts of interviews; notes and excerpts copied from publications, facsimile copies, correspondence, and printed material; correspondence and memoranda; manuscripts; speeches; indexes; clippings; lists; and chronologies. The files were created by Sidney Ralph Bernstein and Marianne Keating, his research assistant, for a commemorative history of the J. Walter Thompson Company at the time of its centennial anniversary. The history was not published. The collection documents the history of J. Walter Thompson Company, especially through personal reminiscences, recollections, and evaluations of the company by its executives and other employees; advertising executives; women in the advertising industry; and J. Walter Thompson, founder of the company.
The Correspondence Series documents the planning phases of the project and the selection of Sidney Ralph Bernstein from a pool of prospective authors. Company executive Milton Moskowitz was primarily responsible for arranging the project but the Executive Committee approved all aspects of it. Bernstein's and Keating's research activities are described throughout the series. The correspondence includes biographical material about various company leaders, including William James Carlton and Stanley B. Resor, and information about the 1918 tax law case against the J. Walter Thompson Company.
A substantial part of the project included interviewing company employees about their personal experiences and about clients. The transcripts of the interviews are in the Oral Interview Transcripts Series. Most of the interviews were indexed and provide access to four areas of information: Agencies and associations, accounts, personalities, and selected topics.
The Biographical Files Series has varying quantities of information about officers and staff, some derived from printed sources and some from personal narratives. Most of the files contain information about more than one executive or staff member since, in many of the narratives, subjects discuss other employees. The International Office Series also contains personal narratives about office histories, chronologies, and client relations. Subjects in the Client Files Series that have the most documentation include Chesebrough-Pond's, Eastman Kodak Company, Kraft Foods Company, Pan American World Airways, and Scott Paper Company.
The topical files in the J. Walter Thompson Company Study, Working Files Series comprise a collection of information on various topics, most of which was created by the J. Walter Thompson Company agency or its executives. The Chapter Files Series includes genealogical information about Mr. J. Walter Thompson and his family. Most of the files in the Chapter Files Series are collections of research material to be used in the manuscript; there are no chapter manuscripts in the series.
Processing Note
Many of the folders contain excerpts, transcriptions, and other forms of copies of newspaper articles, reports, correspondence, and other documents. The folder dates refer to the date of original material, not the date of the copy. The folders were left in their original order.
Advertising -- History; Advertising agencies; Advertising executives; Women in the advertising industry; Bernstein, Sidney Ralph, 1907-; J. Walter Thompson Company -- History -- Sources; J. Walter Thompson Company; Thompson, James Walter, 1847-1928
- Correspondence Series, 1961-1968, undated (bulk 1963-1964).
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes correspondence, memoranda, and manuscript drafts. Arranged chronologically.
  - Authors under consideration, 1961, Apr. 20-1963, May 8 1963, May 6-1968, undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Oral Interview Transcripts Series, 1963-1964, undated
  Arrangement note
  Includes a list of interviewees, transcripts, and indexes. Arranged into two parts: Unrestricted Interviews and Additional Interviews; then alphabetically by the names of the interviewee. One group interview is at the end.
  - List of interviewees, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Unrestricted Interviews
    - Harris, David Campbell, 1964, Jan. (Box 1)
    - Flower, Henry, 1963, Nov. (Box 1)
    - Hawes, Robert, 1964, Nov. (Box 1)
    - King, Margaret, 1963, Nov. (Box 1)
    - Lanigan, Denis, 1964, June (Box 1)
    - Meek, Sam, 1963, Nov. (Box 1)
    - Monsarrat, John, 1964, Feb. (Box 1)
    - Young, James W., 1963, Nov. (Box 1)
  - Additional Interviews
    - Armstrong, Dan, 1964, Jan. (Box 2)
    - Baldwin, Florence, 1964, Jan. (Box 2)
    - Boyle, Joseph, 1963, Nov. (Box 2)
    - Colwell, Robert and O'Meara, Walter, 1963, Nov. (Box 2)
    - Devine, John, 1964, Sept. (Box 2)
    - Henderson, Howard, 1963, Nov. (Box 2)
    - Hinks, Kenneth W., 1963, Nov. (Box 2)
    - Kohl, Howard, 1964, Mar. (Box 2)
    - Lydecker, Garrett, 1963, Nov. (Box 2)
    - Mygatt, Phil, 1964, Jan. (Box 2)
    - O'Meara, Walter, and Colwell, Robert, 1963, Nov. (Box 2)
    - Owett, Bernard, and Seibert, Wilson, 1964, Jan. (Box 2)
    - Perry, William A., 1963, Nov. (Box 2)
    - Rheinstrom, Carl, 1963, Nov. (Box 2)
    - Robinson, Ed, 1964, Jan. (Box 2)
    - Rubicam, Ray, 1964, Jan. (Box 2)
    - Seibert, Wilson, 1963, Nov. (Box 2)
    - Seymour, Dan, 1963, Nov. and 1964, Oct. (Box 2)
    - Stephenson, Nancy, 1963, Oct. (Box 2)
    - Strouse, Norman H., 1963, Nov. and 1964, Feb. (Box 2)
    - Temphest, Margaret, 1963, Nov. (Box 3)
    - Thorburn, Don, 1963, Oct. (Box 3)
    - Vorce, Richard, 1964, Apr. (Box 3)
    - Waldo, Ruth, 1964, May (Box 3)
    - Copywriter's luncheon (Downing, Ruth; Foster, Ann; Littlefield, Mary Jo; Ostrum, Doris), 1963, Nov. (Box 3)
- Biographical Files Series, 1916-1964, undated
  Contains correspondence, notes, resumes, clippings, transcripts of interviews, excerpts, and essays. See also oversize. Arranged alphabetically by the names of the subjects, with a miscellaneous folder at the end.
  - B: Baillie, Lloyd, undated; Bayley, Robert, undated; Benoit, Woodrow, undated; Blomquist, Arthur, 1964; Brady, Curtis, 1963; Buchanan, Robert, undated (Box 4)
  - C: Castle, Robert, 1964; Cherington, Paul T., undated (Box 4)
  - Colwell, Robert Talcott, 1945-1963, undated (Box 4)
  - D: Danker, Jr., Daniel, undated; Day, William L., undated (Box 4)
  - E: Eaton, Seymour, 1916; Esty, John, undated; Esty, William, 1925, undated (Box 4)
  - F: Flower, Henry C. undated; Francisco, Don, undated (Box 4)
  - Gretchell, J. Stirling, 1924-1963, undated (Box 4)
  - G: Gordon, Eli, undated; Grimes, Arthur, undated (Box 4)
  - H: Haynes, Storrs, undated; Herrmann, Harry, undated; Hewitt, Anderson, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Hinks, Kenneth W., 1925-1963 (Box 4)
  - H-J: Hocker, William, 1964; Huff, Clayton, undated; Ireland, Harry M., undated; Johnson, Arno H., undated; Jones, Ruth, undated (Box 4)
  - K-L: Kinney, Gilbert, undated; Kohl, Howard, 1964, undated; Laurie, Jr., William D., 1964; Legler, Henry Mayson, undated; Lemon, Luther Orange, undated; Lochridge,Willard, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Meek, Sam, 1963, undated (Box 4)
  - Mygatt, Phillip, undated (Box 4)
  - O'Meara, Walter, 1963, undated (Box 4)
  - Palmer, William G., undated (Box 4)
  - Perry, William A., 1963 (Box 4)
  - Privett, John A., 1964, undated (Box 4)
  - Raymond, Charles, E., undated (Box 4)
  - Reber, John U., 1964, undated (Box 4)
  - Resor, Helen, undated (Box 4)
  - Resor, Stanley B., 1936-1964, undated (Box 4)
  - Resor, William E., 1919, undated (Box 4)
  - Richey, S. Hunter, undated (Box 4)
  - Robinson, Edward N., 1961-1963, undated (Box 4)
  - Seibert, Wilson, undated (Box 4)
  - Stanton, Henry T., 1954-1964, undated (Box 4)
  - Stephenson, Frank and Stephenson, Nancy F., undated (Box 4)
  - Stevens, Henry, 1963, undated (Box 4)
  - Strouse, Norman H., 1963 (Box 4)
  - Sutton, Thomas F., 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Tarlton, John V., ca. 1958, undated (Box 4)
  - Thompson, W. Roosevelt, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Thorburn, B. Donaldson, 1959-1964, undated (Box 4)
  - Tinker, Jack, undated (Box 4)
  - Van Nest, Dean, undated (Box 5)
  - Waldo, Ruth, 1948-1964, undated (Box 5)
  - Young, James Webb, 1916-1964, undated (Box 5)
  - Watson, Jon Broadcus, undated; Wilson, Edward G., 1960-1965; Woodward, W. E., 1964, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1925, Oct.-1964, June, undated (Box 5)
- International Office Histories Series, 1946-1964, undated (bulk 1963-1964).
  Includes interview transcripts, historical essays and chronologies, correspondence and memoranda, notes, and lists. Arranged with an information file at the beginning; followed by files for various countries, arranged alphabetically by the name of the country.
  - Information and budgets file, 1946, June-1964, Mar., undated (Box 5)
  - Australia, 1963, undated (Box 5)
  - Belgium, 1963, Dec., undated (Box 5)
  - Canada, 1963, Feb.-1964, Aug., undated (Box 5)
  - England, 1964, undated (Box 5)
  - Chile, 1964, Feb., undated (Box 5)
  - India, 1964, undated (Box 5)
  - Italy, 1964, Feb. (Box 5)
  - Mexico, 1964, Feb. (Box 5)
  - Netherlands, 1964, Apr.-1964, July (Box 5)
  - Pakistan, 1964, Feb. (Box 5)
  - Philippines, 1964, Apr. (Box 5)
  - South Africa, 1964, Jan. (Box 5)
  - Sri Lanka, 1963, Feb. (Box 5)
- Client Files Series, 1916-1967, undated
  Includes clippings, notes, correspondence and memoranda, lists, printed material, negatives, speeches, house organs, and advertisements. See also oversize. Arranged alphabetically by the clients' names.
  - Arbuckle Brothers/Yuban Coffee, 1921, Apr-1964, June (Box 5)
  - Chesebrough-Pond's, 1952-1967, Sept., undated (Box 5)
  - Coca Cola, 1929 (Box 5)
  - Eastman Kodak Co., 1960-1965, undated (Box 5)
  - Ford Motor Co., 1916, Aug.-1967, undated (Box 6)
  - General Cigar Co., 1932-1946, July (Box 6)
  - General Motors Co., 1929, June-1963, Aug. (Box 6)
  - J. B. Williams, 1963, Dec. (Box 6)
  - Jergens Co., 1963, Nov.-1964, Apr. (Box 6)
  - Kraft Foods Co., 1926, Jan.-1967, May, undated (Box 6)
  - Lamont, Corliss & Co., undated (Box 6)
  - Lever Brothers Co., 1902, Jan.-1966, May, undated (Box 6)
  - Libby, McNeill & Libby, 1930, Sept.-1965, June, undated (Box 6)
  - Liggett & Myers Tobacco Co., 1964, June-1966, Apr., undated (Box 6)
  - Lorillard, 1941, Apr. (Box 6)
  - Maxwell House Coffee (Cheek-Neal), 1958-1959, undated (Box 6)
  - Mehtholatum Company, 1966, Oct. (Box 6)
  - Pan American World Airways, 1955, Nov.-1967, Jan., undated (Box 6)
  - Phillips Petroleum Co., 1964, Mar.-1965, July (Box 6)
  - Prudential Life Insurance, 1902-1965, undated (Box 6)
  - Puralator Products, 1964, June-1965, Jan. (Box 6)
  - Quaker Oats Co., 1961-1964, June (Box 6)
  - Radio Corporation of America, 1953-1954, undated (Box 6)
  - Religion in American Life campaigns, 1964, Sept.-1966, Jan., undated (Box 6)
  - Scott Paper Co., 1953, Feb.-1965, May, undated (Box 6)
  - Seagram's, 1967, Apr. (Box 6)
  - Seven-Up, 1963, Dec.-1966, Jan., undated (Box 6)
  - Shell, 1916, Sept., undated (Box 6)
  - Singer Co., 1963, Sept.-1964 (Box 6)
  - Standard Brands, 1935, Apr.-1964, Feb., undated (Box 6)
  - Union Central Life Insurance, 1932, Dec. (Box 6)
  - United States Lines, 1964, Feb. (Box 6)
  - United States Playing Card Co., 1916, Sept.-1964, Oct. (Box 6)
  - United States Rubber, undated (Box 6)
  - Warner-Lambert Pharmaceutical Co., 1965, Oct. (Box 6)
  - World's Fair, 1963, Nov.-1964, Mar. (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous: (Box 7)
    - Client Lists: Case History Excerpts, 1916-1964 (Box 7)
    - Coffee marketing and advertising by the J. Walter Thompson Company (short histories of Yuban; Maxwell House; Chase & Sanborn), 1960 (Box 7)
- J. Walter Thompson Company Study, Working Files, 1916-1959, undated
  Consists of speeches; commentaries; notes; and excerpts copied from correspondence, speeches, business files, and publications. Files retain Bernstein's original order and folder titles; information in brackets added for clarification Arranged by file numbers assigned by Bernstein.
  - No. 1, Resor, Stanley B., speech in class 1916 [Resor, Standey B.: speeches, 1916-1919; manuscript for publication, 1919; comments, 1957; Lasker, A. D.: Ad Age (excerpts), 1953; Young, James Webb: comments, 1956] (Box 7)
  - No. 2, Policy Letters [Stanley B. Resor and Samuel Meek, 1920, Apr.-1952, July, undated (Box 7)
  - No. 3, Agency Compensation, 1956, Sept.-1959, undated (Box 7)
  - No. 4, Agency as Unique [comments about JWT solicited by Maurice F. Hanson from other company executives], 1947-1959, Jan. (Box 7)
  - No. 5, JWT and Charles E. Raymond [Excerpts from JWT Advertising Books, JWT Blue Books, Charles E. Raymond ( Reminiscences, 1932) and Frank Presbrey ( History and Development of Advertising, 1929], 1895-1929, undated (Box 7)
  - No. 6, Notes on JWT Study [1950s study by Howard Henderson?], 1916, Feb.-1959, Jan., undated (Box 7)
- J. Walter Thompson Company History Series, 1873-1964, undated (bulk 1960s).
  Includes notes, excerpts, clippings, lists, correspondence, memoranda, house organs, speeches, and writings. Files retain Bernstein's original order and folder titles; information in brackets added for clarification. Arranged alphabetically by folder titles.
  - Clipping file [includes excerpts], 1873-1964, Mar., undated (Box 7)
  - Decor [office descriptions and floor plans], 1947-1964, undated (Box 7)
  - Financial materials, 1917-1964, Mar. (Box 7)
  - Hollywood office history, 1963, Dec.-1964, May (Box 7)
  - J. Walter Thompson Company correspondence [facsimiles], 1893-1917 (Box 7)
  - J. Walter Thompson Company Seminars, 1960, Nov.-1964, undated (Box 7)
  - N.W. Ayer & Son history, undated (Box 7)
  - Previous histories [ JWT News; Howard Henderson], 1935, Jan.-1960, June (Box 7)
  - Published Articles [clippings], 1964, undated (Box 7)
  - Significant dates, 1953-1964, undated (Box 7)
  - Tax case affidavit, 1918-1969 (Box 7)
  - Quotes on advertising and other articles, 1923, Oct.-1964, Feb., undated (Box 8)
  - What We Say About Ourselves in Memoirs, Talks, etc., [Howard Henderson's files] 1956, Sept.-1959, Nov. undated (Box 8)
  - Women [in the J. Walter Thompson Company], 1918, May-1964, undated (Box 8)
- Department Files, 1931-1964, undated
  Includes clippings, excerpts, memoranda, lists, manuscripts, and notes. Files retain Bernstein's original order and folder titles. See also oversize. Arranged with a report on all departments first, then alphabetically by department name.
  - All departments: report by Stanley B. Resor, 1931-1932 (Box 8)
  - Radio department, 1935-1964, undated (Box 8)
  - Research department, 1932-1964, undated (Box 8)
  - Television department, 1957-1964, undated (Box 8)
  - Type department, 1955-1963, undated (Box 8)
- Chapter Files Series, 1873-1964, undated
  Includes correspondence, memoranda, clippings, excerpts, reports, legal papers, research papers, interviews, indexes to chapters, and notes. Dates in parentheses are time spans covered in the chapters. Arranged by numbers assigned to files by Bernstein.
  - Book outline, ca. 1964 (Box 8)
  - 1: J. Walter Thompson himself, 1928-1964, undated (Box 8)
  - 1: J. Walter Thompson himself/ W. Roosevelt Thompson, 1957-1965 (Box 8)
  - 1: J. Walter Thompson himself/ Carlton & Smith [biographical information about William J. Carlton], 1873-1964, undated (Box 8)
  - 2: James Walter Thompson takes over ( 1878-1908), 1900-1966, undated (Box 8)
  - 3: Enter Stanley B. Resor ( 1908-1917), 1908-1963, undated (Box 8)
  - 4: The Salad Years, ( 1916-1930), 1925-1966, undated (Box 9)
  - 5: Radio Enters the Scene, 1964, undated (Box 9)
  - 6: Depression and Defense ( 1930-1941), 1930-1964 (Box 9)
  - 7: War and Its Aftermath ( 1942-1949), 1942-1964, undated (Box 9)
  - 8: Television Busts the Business Wide Open (1937-?), 1964 (Box 9)
  - 9: The Foreign Story ( 1899-1964) (Box 9)
  - 10: Giantism and the End of an Era ( 1950-1964), 1958-1964, undated (Box 9)
  - 11: World-Wide Agency--100 Years Later, 1946-1964, undated (Box 9)
  - 12: Agencies and Their Clients, 1964 (Box 9)
  - 13: Agencies, Business, and Society, 1960s-1964, undated (Box 9)
  - 14: Problems of the Future (Box 9)
  - 1961-1964, undated, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Sources, 1907-1914, undated (Box 9)
  - Questions, 1957-1964, undated (Box 9)
  - Appendices, credits, 1964, undated (Box 9)
- Manuscript Series, 1964.
  Contains the project manuscript. Arranged by chapter numbers.
  - Introduction, etc. (Box 10)
  - Chapters, 1-End, 4 folders (Box 10)
- Oversize Material
  - Biographical Files (Box 11)
    - Young, James Webb, 1957 (Box 11)
  - Client Files
    - Chesebrough-Pond's, 1919 (Box 11)
    - Kraft Foods Co., 1967 (Box 11)
    - Lever Brothers Co., 1940-1964 (Box 11)
    - Northam Warren/Cutex, 1919 (Box 11)
    - Odorono Co., 1919 (Box 11)
    - Phillips Petroleum, 1965 (Box 11)
    - Prudential Insurance Co., 1901-1902 (Box 11)
  - Department Files
    - Television department, 1963 (Box 11)